<!DOCTYPE recipe SYSTEM "../recipes.dtd">
<recipe>
    <title>Apricot Jam</title>
    <meta>
        <dishtype>Jams</dishtype>
        <processnote>Apricot jam has a perfect sweet-tart balance and good gel from the pectin that makes it a standard glaze on many desserts. It is also great in its own right on toast. Using the kernels from the pits adds a complementary almond flavour. There is no need to peel them or add pectin. The fruits cook down enough that just halving them is sufficient.</processnote>
    </meta>
    <ingredients>
        <yield>3 pints</yield>
        <ingredient>
            <quantity>
                <value>1000</value>
                <unit>g</unit>
            </quantity>
            <item>apricots</item>
        </ingredient>
        <ingredient>
            <quantity>
                <value>100</value>
                <unit>g</unit>
            </quantity>
            <item>water</item>
        </ingredient>
        <ingredient>
            <quantity>
                <value>800</value>
                <unit>g</unit>
            </quantity>
            <item>sugar</item>
        </ingredient>
        <ingredient>
            <quantity>
                <value>2</value>
                <unit>tbs</unit>
            </quantity>
            <item>lemon juice</item>
        </ingredient>
    </ingredients>
    <steps>
        <step>Fill a canning kettle with water to the appropriate level and bring to boil. Reduce heat and keep ready at the boil until the jam is ready. Sterilize <equipment>canning jars</equipment> and lids.</step>
        <step>Cut apricots in half along their seam around the pit. Remove the pits, and put the flesh in a pot with at least three times the capacity of the batch.</step>
        <step>Optionally, crack 10 of the pits and remove the kernel inside. Tie the kernels in a cloth bag or put in a tea strainer. Discard the remaining pits.</step>
        <step>Add water and optional kernels to the pot. Cover and bring batch to a boil.</step>
        <step>Uncover and boil until the apricots soften, about <time>10 minutes</time>.</step>
        <step>Add the sugar to the apricots, stir in to dissolve, and return to the boil. Continue to cook, stirring frequently, until the batch reaches <temperature>215</temperature>.</step>
        <step>Add the lemon juice.</step>
        <step>Continue to cook, stirring frequently, until mixture reaches the jellying point, around <temperature>218</temperature> (apricot jam sets after being cooked to a lower temperature than other jams).</step>
        <step>Remove and discard the bag with the kernels.</step>
        <step><procedure>Can</procedure> and seal jars in canning kettle <time>10 minutes</time>.</step>
    </steps>
</recipe>