<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE recipe SYSTEM "../recipes.dtd">
<recipe>
	<title>Cassis</title>
	<meta>
		<dishtype>Ingredients</dishtype>
		<dishtype>Preserves</dishtype>
	</meta>
	<ingredients>
		<ingredient mainingredient="true">
			<quantity>
				<value>1000</value>
				<unit>g</unit>
			</quantity>
			<item>currants</item>
		</ingredient>
		<ingredient>
			<quantity>
				<value>700</value>
				<unit>g</unit>
				<quantity>
					<value>750</value>
					<unit>ml</unit>
				</quantity>
			</quantity>
			<item>brandy</item>
		</ingredient>
		<ingredient>
			<quantity approximate="true">
				<value>450</value>
				<unit>g</unit>
			</quantity>
			<item>sugar</item>
		</ingredient>
	</ingredients>
	<steps>
		<step>Sterilize a <equipment>canning jar</equipment> large enough to hold currants and brandy.</step>
		<step>Wash and stem currants, and remove mouldy ones.</step>
		<step>Run currants through the coarse disk of a food mill to mash. <expanded>Do not use a food processor. <explanation>This would break up the seeds and bring out their bitterness too much.</explanation></expanded></step>
		<step>Add currants and brandy to jar and seal.</step>
		<step>Store in a dark place at room temperature <time>5 months</time>. Occasionally shake the contents gently.</step>
		<step>Sterilize a <equipment>jelly bag</equipment> and drain the mixture into a bowl.</step>
		<step>Move the mixture to a <equipment>colander</equipment> or <equipment>cheese press</equipment> with a collection bowl.</step>
		<step>Like pressing cheese, put a small amount of weight onto the mixture to press out more liquid. and add more weight each time the liquid stops running to press as much liquid as possible. <expanded>Do not increase the weight too fast, which would press some solids into the liquid and make it cloudy.</expanded></step>
		<step optional="true">Reserve the solids and make jam by adding equal weight of sugar and some water.</step>
		<step>Weigh the liquid, and add sugar in the amount of 45% of the liquid weight. Stir well a few minutes to dissolve.</step>
		<step>Strain the liquid through a <equipment>coffee filter</equipment>.</step>
		<step>Bottle, seal, and mature another <time>2 months</time>.</step>
	</steps>
</recipe>
